This tutorial shows how the STM32 firmware should consume the generated planning tables from this repository. The goal is not to run the simulator onboard. The goal is to store compact tables in flash, decode them on the microcontroller, and execute a real match program through navigation and manipulator state machines.
The project splits the problem in two. Expensive search and planning happen offline on the PC. The generated results are exported as C tables. Then the STM32 firmware reads those tables, selects the right plan, and turns each high-level action into navigation and manipulator work on the actual robot.
Think of these files as an interface contract. Layouts describe the field content. Plan tables describe what the robot should do for a chosen layout. Routes describe how to travel between important nodes. None of these files are direct motor commands. They are compact strategic data that firmware still has to interpret.
The layout table says what colors appear in each branch slot for every legal field arrangement. Firmware can use it to filter layout candidates as it observes colors on the robot. But it should not treat this table as a motion script. It only describes field content.
Once firmware knows the layout, it loads exactly one plan row. Each action tells the robot what kind of task to perform next, like picking a lock, dropping a resource, or returning to start. The firmware still has to resolve target nodes, fetch routes, and update match state after success.
The route table is the bridge between strategy and motion. A route entry does not tell the motors what PWM to output. Instead it gives compact junction-level decisions that a navigation state machine can consume while line following and detecting markers.
The guide recommends a HAL-style split so planning logic, navigation, and manipulation stay decoupled. The match module coordinates the round. Match state stores logical progress. The plan executor decodes the current action. The route wrapper handles lookups. The navigation state machine handles closed-loop movement. The manipulator module handles pickup and drop behavior. The fallback module covers failure paths and uncertain inference states.
The generated files are static flash data, but execution still needs runtime state. Firmware should track where the robot logically is, what it is carrying, which branch tasks are complete, how many layouts remain possible, and which action index is currently active. Keeping this state explicit makes retries, debugging, and fallback behavior much easier.
This is the core firmware-side pattern to remember. The generated plan does not directly move the robot. Instead the firmware repeatedly chooses the current action, resolves the destination node, looks up a route, runs navigation, performs the physical action, updates logical state, and only then advances to the next action.
Each action type has a consistent decode rule. Pick-lock actions map directly to branch lock nodes. Pick-resource actions map to one of the two branch slot nodes. Drop-resource actions map by color to scoring zones. Drop-lock is special because firmware must choose the nearest black zone dynamically. End-round is also special because it needs no route lookup at all.
The cleanest way to run all this on STM32 is with a scheduler-driven match state machine. One state chooses the layout. One selects the current action. One runs navigation. One runs the manipulator. One applies the result. This structure makes timing, retries, and timeout handling much easier than trying to do everything inside one giant function.
The fastest way to validate the architecture is to ignore onboard inference first. Start with a known layout identifier, load that plan from flash, and prove that the robot can execute action after action in the right order. This is the best first milestone because it isolates navigation, manipulation, and state updates before adding inference complexity.
Once the known-layout path works, firmware can graduate to full inference mode. The tracker starts with all legal layouts active. Every observed branch slot color removes inconsistent candidates. When only one layout remains, firmware locks that identifier and loads the matching plan. Until then, the robot should stay in a safe observation or fallback behavior.
Here is the full mental model in one example. If the next action is pick-resource on the blue branch first slot, firmware resolves the target node, gets the route, navigates there, performs the pickup, updates the logical state, and then advances the plan index. That same pattern repeats across most action types with only the decode rule and completion logic changing.
A practical firmware integration needs explicit fallback policy. If a route entry is invalid, that is a table or integration error and should be treated seriously. If manipulation fails repeatedly, firmware should retry only within safe limits and then switch to fallback behavior. And if layout inference is still ambiguous, the robot should not pretend it knows the plan.
The key idea is simple: offline planning gives you compact strategic data, and firmware turns that data into robust closed-loop execution. Start with a known layout, validate the action decode and route flow, then add inference once the basics are solid. If you keep the responsibilities separated, the generated files become a very practical embedded interface.